Grandpa!
You're not supposed to
be up here,
looking at that.
I just wanted to know.
Well, you're old enough,
I suppose.
You should know the story.
OK, here we go.
It was 1832.
On a night much like this.
Charles Carroll was
the last surviving signer of
the Declaration of Independence.
He was also a member of
a secret society
known as the Masons.
And he knew he was dying.
He woke up his stable boy
in the middle of the night
and ordered him to take
him to the White House
to see Andrew Jackson,
because it was urgent
that he speak to the president.
Did he talk to him?
No. He never got the chance.
The president wasn't there
that night.
But Charles Carroll had a secret.
So he took into his confidence
the one person he could,
my grandfather's grandfather,
Thomas Gates.
What was the secret?
A treasure.
A treasure beyond
all imagining.
A treasure that had been
fought over for centuries
by tyrants, pharaohs,
emperors, warlords.
And every time it changed
hands, it grew larger.
And then suddenly...
it vanished.
It didn't reappear for
more than a thousand years,
when knights from
the First Crusade
discovered secret vaults
beneath the Temple of Solomon.
You see, the knights
who found the vaults
believed that the treasure
was too great for any one man -
not even a king.
They brought the treasure
back to Europe
and took the name
"the Knights Templar".
Over the next century
they smuggled it out of Europe
and they formed
a new brotherhood
called the Freemasons,
in honour of the builders of
the great temple.
War followed.
By the time of
the American Revolution
the treasure had been
hidden again.
By then the Masons included
George Washington,
Benjamin Franklin, Paul Revere.
They knew they had to
make sure
the treasure would never fall
into the hands of the British.
So they devised a series of clues
and maps to its location.
Over time the clues
were lost or forgotten,
until only one remained -
and that was the secret
that Charles Carroll entrusted
to young Thomas Gates.
Charlotte.
"The secret lies with Charlotte."
Who's Charlotte?
Oh, not even Mr Carroll
knew that.
Now look here, Ben.
The Freemasons among our
Founding Fathers left us clues.
Like these.
The unfinished pyramid.
The all-seeing eye.
Symbols of the Knights Templar,
guardians of the treasure.
They're speaking to us
through these.
You mean laughing at us.
You know what
that dollar represents?
The entire Gates family fortune.
Six generations of fools...
chasing after fool's gold.
It's not about the money,
Patrick.
It's never been about
the money.
Come on, son. Time to go.
You can... say your goodbyes.
Grandpa?
Are we knights?
Do you want to be?
All right. Um... kneel.
Benjamin Franklin Gates,
you take upon yourself
the duty of the Templars,
the Freemasons,
and the family Gates.
Do you so swear?
I so swear.
I was thinking about
Henson and Peary,
crossing this kind of terrain
with nothing more than
dog sleds and on foot.
- Can you imagine?
- It's extraordinary.
We getting closer?
Assuming Ben's theory
is correct
and my tracking model's
accurate,
we should be getting
very close.
But don't go by me -
I broke a shoelace this morning.
It's... it's a bad omen.
Shall we turn around
and go home?
Or we could pull over
and just throw him out here.
OK.
Riley, you're not missing that
little windowless cubicle
we found you in, are you?
No, no. Absolutely not.
Why are we stopping?
I thought we were
looking for a ship.
- I don't see any ship.
- She's out there.
Look... this is a waste of time.
How could a ship wind up
way out here?
Well, I'm no expert, but...
it could be that the hydrothermic
properties of this region
produce hurricane-force
ice storms
that cause the ocean to freeze
and then melt and then refreeze,
resulting in a semisolid
migrating land mass
that would land a ship
right around here.
Hello, beautiful.
Have Viktor check the fuel
in the generators.
Two years ago,
if you hadn't shown up,
hadn't believed
the treasure was real,
I don't know if I ever
would have found Charlotte.
You would have found it,
I have no doubt.
That's why I didn't
think it was
as crazy an investment as
everyone said.
I'm just relieved that I'm not
as crazy as everyone says.
Or said my dad was.
Or my granddad.
Or my great-granddad.
OK!
Let's go!
- Let's go find some treasure.
- Yeah, bring us back something.
Oh, God!
You handled that well.
This is it.
It's the cargo hold.
Do you think it's in the barrels?
Gunpowder.
Why would the captain
be guarding this barrel?
I found something!
What is it?
Do you guys know
what this is?
Is it a billion-dollar pipe?
It's a meerschaum pipe.
Ah, that is beautiful.
Look at the intricacy of the
scrollwork on the stem.
- Is it a million-dollar pipe?
- No, it's a clue.
Let me see that.
No, don't break it!
We are one step closer
to the treasure, gentlemen.
Ben, I thought you said that
the treasure would be
on the Charlotte.
No, "The secret lies with Charlotte."
I said it could be here.
It's Templar symbols.
"The legend writ."
"The stain effected."
"The key in Silence undetected."
"Fifty-five in iron pen."
"Mr Matlack can't offend."
It's a riddle.
I need to think.
"The legend writ."
"The stain effected."
What legend?
There's the legend of
the Templar treasure,
and the stain effects
the legend.
How?
"The key in Silence undetected."
Wait.
The legend and the key...
Now there's something.
A map.
Maps have legends,
maps have keys.
It's a map, an invisible map.
So now...
Wait a minute.
What do you mean, "invisible"
"an invisible map"?
"The stain effected"
could refer to a dye
or a reagent used to bring
about a certain result.
Combined with
"The key in Silence undetected",
the implication is that
the effect is to make what
was undetectable detectable.
Unless...
"The key in Silence" could be...
Prison.
Albuquerque.
See, I can do it too.
Snorkel.
That's where the map is.
Like he said,
"Fifty-five in iron pen."
"Iron pen" is a prison.
Or it could be,
since the primary writing medium
of the time was iron gall ink,
the "pen" is... just a pen.
But then why not say a pen?
Why... why say "iron pen"?
Cos it's a prison.
Wait a minute.
"Iron pen" - the "iron" does not
describe the ink in the pen,
it describes what was penned.
It was "iron" -
it was firm, it was mineral...
No, no, no, that's stupid.
It was... It was firm,
it was adamant, it was resolved.
It was resolved.
"Mr Matlack can't offend."
Timothy Matlack was
the official scribe
of the Continental Congress.
Calligrapher, not writer.
And to make sure
he could not offend the map,
it was put on the back
of a resolution
that he transcribed,
a resolution
that 55 men signed.
The Declaration of Independence.
Come on,
there's no invisible map
on the back of the
Declaration of Independence.
That's clever, really.
A document of that importance
would ensure the map's survival.
And you said there were
several Masons signed it, yeah?
Yeah. Nine, for sure.
We'll have to arrange
a way to examine it.
This is one of the most important
documents in history.
They're not just gonna let us
waltz in there and
run chemical tests on it.
- Then what do you propose we do?
- I don't know!
We could borrow it.
Steal it?
- I don't think so.
- Ben...
The treasure of the Knights Templar
is the treasure of all treasures.
Oh, I didn't know that.
Really?
Look, Ben...
I understand your bitterness.
I really do.
You've spent your entire life
searching for this treasure,
only to have the respected
historical community
treat you and your family
with mockery and contempt.
You should be able to rub this
treasure in their arrogant faces,
and I want you to have
the chance to do that.
How?
We all have our areas
of expertise.
You don't think mine are limited
to writing cheques, do you?
In another life...
I arranged a number of
operations of...
questionable legality.
I'd take his word for it,
if I were you.
So don't worry.
I'll make all the arrangements.
No.
I'd really need your help here.
Ian...
I'm not gonna let you steal the
Declaration of Independence.
OK.
From this point on all you're
going to be is a hindrance.
Hey!
What are you gonna do?
Are you gonna shoot me, Shaw?
Well, you can't shoot me.
There's more to the riddle.
Information you don't have.
I do.
I'm the only one
who can figure it out,
and you know that.
He's bluffing.
We played poker together, Ian.
You know I can't bluff.
Tell me what I need
to know, Ben,
or I'll shoot your friend.
Hey!
Quiet, Riley!
Your job's finished here.
Look where you're standing.
All that gunpowder.
You shoot me,
I drop this, we all go up.
Ben...
What happens when
the flare burns down?
Tell me what I need
to know, Ben.
You need to know...
if Shaw can catch.
Nice try, though, you know.
Get out, Shaw!
Fool!
Riley, get over here!
- What is this?
- Smuggler's hold. Get in!
Move! Get out of here!
- What?
- Move! Get out!
Follow me.
Let's go, let's go!
She's gonna blow!
Get down.
OK, let's go.
Before someone sees the smoke.
There's an Inuit village
about nine miles east of here.
- It's popular with bush pilots.
- All right.
- Then what are we gonna do?
- Start making our way back home.
No, I meant about Ian.
He's gonna steal the Declaration
of Independence, Ben
We stop him.
Is it really so hard to believe that
someone's gonna try to steal
the Declaration of Independence?
The FBI gets 10,000 tips a week.
They're not gonna worry about
something they're sure is safe.
But anyone that can do anything
is gonna think we're crazy.
Anyone crazy enough to believe us
isn't gonna want to help.
We don't need someone crazy.
But one step short of crazy,
what do you get?
Obsessed.
Passionate.
Excuse me.
Dr Chase can see you now,
Mr Brown.
Thank you.
Mr Brown?
The family name doesn't
get a lot of respect
in the academic community.
Being kept down by the man.
A very cute man.
Thank you.
- Good afternoon, gentlemen.
- Hi.
- Abigail Chase.
- Paul Brown.
- Nice to meet you.
- Bill.
Nice to meet you, Bill.
- How may I help you?
- Your accent. Pennsylvania Dutch?
Saxony German.
- You're not American?
- Oh, I am an American.
I just wasn't born here.
Please don't touch that!
Sorry. A neat collection.
George Washington's
campaign buttons.
You're missing the 1789
inaugural, though.
- I found one once.
- That's very fortunate for you.
Now, you told my assistant
that this was an urgent matter.
Yes, ma'am.
Well, I'm gonna get
straight to the point.
Someone's gonna steal the
Declaration of Independence.
It's true.
I think I'd better put
you gentlemen
in touch with the FBI.
- We've been to the FBI.
- And?
They assured us that
the Declaration
cannot possibly be stolen.
- They're right.
- My friend and I are less certain.
However...
if we were given the privilege
of examining the document...
we would be able to
tell you for certain
if it were actually
in any danger.
What do you think
you're gonna find?
We believe that there's an...
encryption on the back.
- An encryption, like a code?
- Yes, ma'am.
Of what?
A... cartograph.
- A map.
- Yes, ma'am.
A map of what?
The location of...
of hidden items of historic
and intrinsic value.
- A treasure map?
- That's where we lost the FBI.
You're treasure-hunters,
aren't you?
We're more like
treasure-protectors.
Mr Brown,
I have personally seen
the back of the Declaration
of Independence,
and I promise you,
the only thing there
is a notation that reads,
"Original Declaration
of Independence dated..."
"dated four of July, 1776."
Yes, ma'am.
But no map.
It's invisible.
Oh! Right.
And that's where we lost
the Department of
Homeland Security.
What led you to assume
there's this invisible map?
We found an engraving on the
stem of a 200-year-old pipe.
Owned by Freemasons.
- May I see the pipe?
- We don't have it.
- Did Big Foot take it?
- It was nice meeting you.
Nice to meet you, too.
And, you know,
that really is a nice collection.
Must have taken you a long time
to hunt down all that history.
If it's any consolation,
you had me convinced.
It's not.
I was thinking,
what if we go public,
plaster the story
all over the Internet?
It's not like we have our
reputations to worry about.
Although...
I don't think that's exactly
gonna scare Ian away.
180 years of searching,
and I'm three feet away.
Of all the ideas that
became the United States,
there's a line here that's
at the heart of all the others.
"But when a long train
of abuses and usurpations,
pursuing invariably
the same object,
evinces a design to reduce them
under absolute despotism,
it is their right, it is their duty
to throw off such government
and provide new guards
for their future security."
People don't talk that
way any more.
Beautiful, huh?
No idea what you said.
It means,
if there's something wrong,
those who have the ability
to take action
have the responsibility
to take action.
I'm gonna steal it.
What?
I'm gonna steal the
Declaration of Independence.
Ben?
This is... huge.
Prison huge.
You are gonna go to prison,
you know that?
Yeah, probably.
So that would bother
most people.
Ian's gonna try and steal it.
And if he succeeds,
he'll destroy the Declaration.
The fact is...
the only way to protect
the Declaration is to steal it.
It's upside down.
I don't think there's a choice.
Ben, for God's sakes,
it's like stealing
a national monument. OK?
It's like stealing him.
It can't be done.
Not shouldn't be done.
Let me prove it to you.
OK, Ben, pay attention.
I've brought you to
the Library of Congress.
Why?
Because it's the biggest
library in the world.
Over 20 million books.
And they're all saying
the same exact thing:
Listen to Riley.
What we have here,
my friend,
is an entire layout of
the archives.
Short of builders' blueprints.
You've got construction orders,
phone lines,
water and sewage -
it's all here.
Now, when the Declaration
is on display, OK,
it is surrounded by guards
and video monitors
and a little family from lowa
and little kids on their
eighth-grade field trip.
And beneath an inch
of bulletproof glass
is an army of sensors
and heat monitors
that will go off if someone gets
too close with a high fever.
Now, when it's not on display,
it is lowered into
a four-foot-thick concrete,
steel-plated vault...
that happens to be equipped
with an electronic combination lock
and biometric
access-denial systems.
You know, Thomas Edison tried
and failed nearly 2,000 times
to develop the carbonised
cotton-thread filament
for the incandescent light bulb.
Edison?
When asked about it,
he said, "I didn't fail,
I found out 2,000 ways
how not to make a light bulb."
But he only needed to find
one way to make it work.
The Preservation Room.
Enjoy. Go ahead.
Do you know what the
Preservation Room is for?
Delicious jams and jellies?
No. That's where they clean,
repair and maintain
all the documents
and the storage housings
when they're not
on display or in the vault.
Now, when the case needs work
they take it out of the vault,
directly across the hall and
into the Preservation Room.
The best time for us,
or Ian,
to steal it would be during
the gala this weekend
when the guards are distracted
by the VIPs upstairs.
But we'll make our way to
the Preservation Room,
where there's much
less security.
Well, if Ian...
Preservation...
The gala?
This might be possible.
It might.
And we are in.
There you are.
Hello.
The hallway.
That's what I want.
Game on.
I'll buy that.
Cool.
This just came for you.
I hope it's not from Stan.
"For the woman
who has everything else...
Thanks for listening.
Paul Brown."
Abigail Chase.
Hey, Mike.
- Let's do this by the book.
- Hallway is secure.
- Keep the document level.
- No problem.
What have you got?
The heat sensor went off
in the Declaration frame.
Run full diagnostics,
then I want them
all changed out.
Our evil plan is working.
Ben, are you sure
that we should...?
Riley.
- Can you hear me?
- Unfortunately, yeah.
We're all set in here.
You want to go around
to the front
and present your invitation.
You're gonna have to show ID.
Go ahead, man.
Howdy.
I need your invitation
and your ID, please.
How do you look?
- Not bad.
- Mazel tov.
This is it.
For you.
- Oh, Mr Brown.
- Dr Chase.
- What are you doing here?
- Is that that hot girl?
How does she look?
I made a last-minute donation.
Pretty big one.
Well, on that subject,
thank you for your
wonderful gift.
- Oh, you did get it? Good.
- Yes, thank you.
You know,
I really couldn't accept
something like that normally,
but...
I really want it.
Well, you needed it.
Come on, Romeo,
get outta there.
I have been wondering,
though,
what the engraving
indicated
on the pipe that
Big Foot took.
Hi.
- Here you go.
- Oh, Dr Herbert, this is Mr Brown.
- Hi.
- Hi there.
Who's the stiff?
Here, why don't you
let me take that?
So you can take that
off his hands.
Thank you.
A toast, yeah?
To high treason.
That's what these men
were committing
when they signed
the Declaration.
Had we lost the war,
they would have been hanged,
beheaded, drawn and
quartered,
and - oh!
Oh, my personal favourite..
and had their entrails
cut out and burned!
So, here's to the men who did
what was considered wrong
in order to do what
they knew was right.
What they knew was right.
Well, good night.
- Good night.
Yeah!
OK, go! Go!
This better work.
Clear!
- On.
- Door one. 30 seconds.
How does it look?
It's working.
It's working...
Unbelievable.
Second door. 90 seconds.
Well done, boys. Let's go.
- We're in the elevator.
- OK.
I'm gonna turn off the
surveillance cameras. Ready?
In five, four,
three... Now.
Ben Gates,
you are now the Invisible Man.
I'm here.
Give me the letters
for her password.
What do you got for me?
Hit me with it.
A-E-F-G...
L-O-R-V-Y.
Anagrams being listed.
OK.
Top results: "A glove fry."
"A very golf."
"Fargo levy."
"Gravy floe. Valey frog."
Also "Ago fly rev."
"Grove fly a."
"Are fly gov."
"Era fly gov."
- "Elf gov ray."
- It's "Valley Forge".
"Valley For..." I don't have
that on my computer.
It's "Valley Forge" -
she pressed the E and L twice.
We're in.
Hello.
Ben, you're doing great.
Ben, pick it up.
You got about one...
We own video.
- I lost my feed.
- What?
I lost my feed, Ben.
I don't know
where anyone is.
I have nothing.
Ben, I have no...
Ben, I have nothing.
Get out of there.
Get out of there now.
I'm taking the whole thing.
I'll get it out in the elevator.
What are you talking about?
Is it heavy?
Shaw. Door three, one minute.
Gates.
What was that?
Who's shooting?
- Damn.
- He's got the bloody map!
Are you still there?
Ben?
I'm in the elevator.
Ian's here.
There was, uh, shooting.
I hate that guy.
Hey, Rebecca.
Do you have a Paul Brown
on that list?
Paul Brown?
No. Not here.
Have a good night.
Are you trying to steal that?
It's $35.
- For this?
- Yeah.
- That's a lot.
- Hey, I don't make the prices.
It's...
I have $32...
57 c.
We take Visa.
This is Mike. Sublevel three.
I have an alert.
Where are you, Ben?
- Where are you?
- Stop talking.
Start the van.
Ben, the...
the mean Declaration
lady's behind you.
Hey.
Oh, it's you. Hello.
Mr Brown, what's going on?
What's that?
- It's a souvenir.
- Really?
Stop chatting
and get in the van.
Code red. Code red.
We have a break-in.
Lock it down.
Nobody leaves the building.
Get the FBI on the phone.
- Did you enjoy the party?
- Yeah.
- Oh, my God.
- Oh, my God! You did not...?
- No...
- Security! Over here!
- Give me that!
- It's yours. Take it.
Security!
- Over here! Security!
- Got you.
Go.
Viktor! Move!
- We can't just let her go!
- We can. Go!
- Security, over here!
- Wait. No, hold it.
Hold it!
- Wha...?
- Oh, bad.
- What do you want?
- Give me the document.
- No way!
- Bad, bad, bad!
- Let me go!
- Just bring her!
No! No!
- That's...
- Go! Go!
And just who might you be?
Once we catch them
what we gonna do?
I'm working on it.
Right turn, right turn.
Why don't you just pass
me that document?
Then we can all go home.
Oh, no.
Skidding, skidding, skidding.
- Oh, no!
- Holy Lord!
Help!
No! If she falls,
the document falls.
Get me next to her.
- Thank you.
- No!
Got it. Go on.
Abigail!
Come on. Jump.
We lost them.
That's all right.
This... is what we need.
Well done, Gates.
Well done.
- Are you all right?
- No! Those lunatics...
- You're not hurt, are you?
- You are all lunatics!
- Are you hungry?
- What?
Are you all right?
Still a little on edge
from being shot at,
but I'll be OK.
Thanks for asking.
Yeah, well, I'm not all right.
Those men have the
Declaration of Independence!
- She lost it?
- They don't have it.
See? OK?
Now could you please
stop shouting?
Give me that!
You're still shouting.
And it's really starting to annoy.
You'd do well, Dr Chase,
to be a bit more civilised
in this instance.
If this is the real one,
what did they get?
A souvenir.
I thought it'd be a good idea
to have a duplicate.
It turned out I was right.
I actually had to pay for the
souvenir and the real one,
so you owe me $35,
plus tax.
- Genius.
- Who were those men?
Just the guys we warned you
were gonna steal the Declaration.
And you didn't believe us.
We did the only thing
we could do to keep it safe.
Verdammt! Give me that!
You know something?
You're shouting again.
I'm pretty sure
she was swearing, too.
Well, we probably deserve that.
Ladies and gentlemen...
Ladies and gentlemen,
my name is Peter Sadusky.
I'm the agent in charge.
I wanna reassure you,
you are not in danger in any way.
If we all cooperate,
we'll get through this with
as little frustration as possible.
Thank you.
Get positive IDs.
Search everyone,
including the security staff.
If they refuse,
detain them and get warrants.
Yes, Agent Hendricks?
You have something?
Um...
This isn't a day for "Um..."
We got a tip several days ago
that someone was going to steal
the Declaration of Independence.
Do we have a name
on the tipster?
There was no file opened.
We didn't find
the information credible.
How about now?
There is not a treasure map
on the back of the
Declaration of Independence.
And there's no chance
anyone can steal this either.
I levelled with you
100 per cent.
Everything I told you
was the truth.
I want that document,
Mr Brown.
OK, my name's not Brown.
It's Gates.
I levelled with you
98 per cent.
Wait a minute,
did you just say "Gates"?
Gates?
You're that family with
the conspiracy theory
about the Founding Fathers?
- It's not a conspiracy theory.
- Per se.
You know what?
I take it back.
You're not liars.
You're insane.
There's a copy of the
Declaration on display now?
- Yes, we decided to...
- Leave it there.
The guests know
something happened,
but they don't know what.
They got him with a Taser
at the service entrance.
He doesn't remember a thing.
Also, we found bullet casings.
Did we get a description
from the other guards?
- Which guards?
- The guards that were fired upon.
There weren't any other
guards on patrol down here.
So...
who was shooting,
who were they shooting at,
and why weren't they
getting along?
You can't seriously intend
to run chemical tests
on the Declaration of
Independence
in the back of a moving van.
We have a clean-room
environment all set up.
EDS suits, a particulate
air filtration system,
the whole shebang.
- Really?
- We can't go back there.
What? Why not?
This is the guy.
Dr Herbert said Dr Chase
introduced him as Mr Brown.
Not on the guestlist.
Now, the gift-store clerk -
she saidhe seemed...
Well, she said "flustered".
He tried to walk out
with a copy
of the Declaration of
Independence without paying.
He paid with a Visa.
Charge to Benjamin Gates.
A credit-card slip?
Dude, we're on the grid.
They'll have your records
from forever.
They'll have my records
I know. I know. It's
only a matter of minutes
before the FBI shows up
at my front door.
What do we do?
- We need those letters.
- What letters?
You know, get off the road,
take a right.
What letters?
You have the original
Silence Dogood letters?
Did you steal those, too?
We have scans of the originals.
- Quiet, please.
- How'd you get scans?
Oh, I know the person
who has the originals.
Now shush.
Why do you need them?
She really can't shut her
mouth, can she?
I'll tell you what, look.
I will let you hold onto this
if you'll promise to shut up,
please.
Thank you.
Ben, you know
what you have to do.
I know what to do.
I'm just trying to think
of anything else we could do.
Well, not to be a... nudge,
but you do realise how many
people we have after us.
We probably have
our own satellite by now.
It took you all of two seconds
to decide to steal the
Declaration of Independence.
Yeah, but I didn't think
I was gonna personally
have to tell my dad about it.
Hey, not cool! Not cool!
Let me go!
OK. You're let go. Go, shoo.
I'm not going.
Not without the Declaration.
You're not going
with the Declaration.
Yes, I am. I'm not letting it
out of my sight, so I'm going.
Wait. You're not going
with us with the Declaration.
- Yes, I am.
- No, you're not.
Look, if you wanted to
leave me behind,
you shouldn't have told me
where you were going.
Clear.
What the...
Now we're getting
somewhere.
They're digital scans
of letters
to the editor of
The New England Courant.
Written 1722.
They're all from
the same person.
"Your humble servant,
Silence Dogood."
Gentlemen...
why is this word capitalised?
Because it's important?
Because it's a name.
OK, I got it.
When Ben Franklin was
only 15 years old
he secretly wrote 14 letters
to his brother's newspaper
pretending to be a middle-aged
widow named Silence Dogood.
These letters were written
by Benjamin Franklin.
Looks OK.
Park a couple of blocks
away.
Well, how long do you
think we got?
I'm gonna give them
a couple of hours at least.
I hope.
What do we do about her?
I've got some duct
tape in the back.
No, that won't be necessary.
She won't be any trouble.
Promise you won't be
any trouble.
I promise.
See? She's curious.
Here's what I got on Gates.
A degree in American History
from Georgetown,
a degree in Mechanical
Engineering at MIT,
Navy ROTC and Naval Diving
and Salvage Training Centre.
What in the world did this guy
want to be when he grew up?
We keep our focus on Gates.
Run him to ground.
Compile a family-and-friends list.
Closest relative first.
I want to find out
who this guy is.
Dad.
Where's the party?
Well... I'm in a little trouble.
Is she pregnant?
Well, if she is, are you
gonna leave the woman
carrying your grandchild
standing out in the cold?
I look pregnant?
This better not be about
that dumb treasure.
Well, have a seat.
Make yourselves comfortable.
There's some pizza.
It's still warm, I think.
Dad...
I need the Silence Dogood
letters.
Yeah,
it's about the treasure.
And he dragged you two
into this nonsense?
- Literally.
- I volunteered.
Well, unvolunteer,
before you waste your life.
Knock it off, Dad.
Sure, sure, I know,
I'm the family kook.
I have a job, a house,
health insurance.
At least I had your mother,
for however brief a time.
At least I had you.
What do you have? Him?
Look, if you just give us
the letters, we're gone.
You disappoint me, Ben.
Well, maybe that's the
real Gates-family legacy.
Sons who disappoint
their fathers.
Get out.
Take your troubles with you.
I found the Charlotte.
The Charlotte?
- You mean she was a ship?
- Yeah, she was beautiful.
It was amazing, Dad.
And the treasure?
No, no. But we found another
clue that led us here.
Yeah, and that'll lead you
to another clue.
And that's all you'll ever find,
is another clue.
Don't you get it, Ben?
I finally figured it out.
The legend says that
the treasure was buried
to keep it from the British.
But what really happened
was the legend was invented,
to keep the British occupied
searching for buried treasure.
The treasure is a myth.
I refuse to believe that.
Well, you can believe
what you want.
You're a grown person.
What am I doing?
Do what you want, Ben.
Do what you want.
He's probably right.
You don't even know
if there is another clue.
Well, I can think of a way
where we could find out.
And we can find out right now.
Looks like animal skin.
- How old is it?
- At least 200 years.
- Really? You sure?
- Pretty darn.
Now if this thing's in
invisible ink,
how do we look at it?
Throw it in the oven.
- No.
- Uh-uh.
Ferrous sulphate inks can only
be brought out with heat.
- Yes, but this...
- It's very old.
This is very old, and we can't
risk compromising the map.
You need a reagent.
Dad, it's really late.
Why don't you get some rest?
I'm fine.
Lemons.
- You can't do that.
- But it has to be done.
Then someone who is trained
to handle antique documents
is gonna do it.
OK.
Now, if there is a secret message,
it'll probably be marked
by a symbol
in the upper
right-hand corner.
That's right.
I am so getting fired for this.
I told you. You need heat.
See?
- We need more juice.
- We need more heat.
That's not a map.
- Is it?
- More clues. What a surprise.
Are those latitudes
and longitudes?
That's why we need
the Silence Dogood letters.
That's the key?
Yeah.
"The key in Silence undetected."
Dad, can we have
the letters now?
Will somebody please
explain to me
what these magic numbers are?
- It's an Ottendorf cipher.
- That's right.
Oh, OK.
- What's an Ottendorf cipher?
- They're just codes.
Each of these three numbers
corresponds to a word in a key.
Usually a random book
or a newspaper article.
In this case,
the Silence Dogood letters.
So it's like the page
number of the key text,
the line on the page,
and the letter in that line.
So, Dad, where are the letters?
You know, it's just by sheer
happenstance that
his grandfather...
- Dad.
- ...even found them.
They were in an antique desk
- from the press room...
- Dad.
of The New England Courant.
- That's a newspaper.
- Dad, where are the letters?
I don't have them, son.
- What?
- I don't have them.
Where are they?
I donated them to the Franklin
Institute in Philadelphia.
Time to go.
I still can't believe it.
All this time no one knew
what was on the back.
The back of what?
No!
- Oh, my God. Oh, my God.
- I know.
Oh, my God.
What have you done?
- This is... this is... this is...
- I know!
the Declaration of
Independence.
Yes. And it's very delicate.
You stole it?
Dad, I can explain,
but I don't have time.
It was necessary.
And you saw the cipher.
And that will lead to another clue,
and that will lead to another clue!
There is no treasure.
I wasted 20 years of my life.
And now you've
destroyed yours.
And you pulled me
into all this.
Well, we can't have that.
Come in!
I'm in here.
FBI, right?
You gonna untie me?
And you have no idea
where he's going?
Well, wouldn't I have
told you if I did?
Would you?
He tied me to a chair.
The garage is empty,
but there's a Cadillac De Ville
registered to Patrick Gates.
And he stole my car.
Don't worry, Mr Gates,
we'll find your car.
And your son.
Your dad's got a sweet ride.
I think we should
change clothes.
We look kind of conspicuous,
don't you think?
I'd love to go shopping, too,
but we have no money.
Here, I took this from his house.
He usually tucks a few
hundred dollars
somewhere between those pages.
- Common Sense. How appropriate.
- When are we gonna get there?
I'm hungry.
This car smells weird.
Excuse me.
Excuse me. Oops, sorry, sir.
That's OK.
S-S-A-N-D.
OK.
You're sure this is right?
S-S-A...
No, N.
- That is an N.
- It doesn't look like an N.
You know what?
Here. Last one. OK?
- One more dollar.
- Thank you.
Go get the last four letters.
Go get 'em, chief. Come on.
OK.
"The vision to see the
treasured past
comes as the timely shadow
crosses in front of
the house of pass and..."
"Pass and..." what?
"Pass and..."
What's going on?
- I'm not sure.
- What's up?
So you show up at your father's
door and say you're in trouble
and the first thing he
assumes is I'm pregnant.
Is there a question in there?
I think there's an interesting
story in there.
Well, my father thinks
I've been a little too cavalier
in my personal life.
- I see.
- Let me ask you something.
Have you ever told someone -
not a relative - "I love you"?
Yes.
More than one someone?
Oh. Well,
then my father would say
you've been a little too cavalier
in your personal life, too.
So you get your sense of absolute
certainty from him, do you?
Well, I'm sure I don't know
what you mean.
Well, you're certain
the treasure is real,
despite what anyone else thinks.
No, but I hope it's real.
I mean,
I've dreamt it's real
since my grandfather
told me about it.
But I want to hold it.
I feel like I'm so close,
I can taste it.
But I just...
I just want to know it's not
just something in my head
or in my heart.
People don't really talk
that way, you know.
I know.
But they think that way.
Hey.
- Did you get it? Riley?
- Oh, I got it.
"The vision to see
the treasured past
comes as the timely shadow
crosses in front of the
house of Pass and Stow."
Now, "Pass and Stow", of course,
referring to...
- The Liberty Bell.
- Why do you have to do that?
Well, John Pass and
John Stow cast the bell.
OK. Well, then, what does
the rest of this mean?
Wait..."The vision to see
the treasured past"
must refer to a way
to read the map.
Well, I thought the cipher
was the map.
No, the cipher was a way
to find the way to read the map.
And the way to read the map
can be found where
the "timely shadow"
crosses in front of
the Liberty Bell.
Crosses in front of the
"house" of the Liberty Bell.
Independence Hall.
Right, so "timely shadow" -
it's a specific time.
- Right.
- What time?
What time? What time?
Wait a minute, wait.
You're gonna love this.
Excuse me, can I see one of
those hundred-dollar bills
I paid you with?
No.
Oh. Well, here,
I have this diver's watch.
It's called a Submariner.
I dive with it.
It's actually quite valuable.
- You can use it as collateral.
- Whatever.
Thank you.
On the back of
a hundred-dollar bill
is an etching of
Independence Hall
- based on a painting done in...
- Hello.
Thank you.
...in the 1780s, who...
The artist was actually
a friend of Benjamin Franklin's.
It's wonderful.
- Fascinating.
- Hold this.
OK.
I'm not going anywhere.
Now, I think that if we look
at this clock tower...
we may find the specific time.
- What do you see?
- 2:22.
- What time is it now?
- Almost three.
- We missed it.
- No, we didn't.
We didn't miss it because...
You don't know this?
I-I know something about
history that you don't know.
I'd be very excited to learn
about it, Riley.
Well, hold on one second,
let me just...
let me just take in
this moment.
This is... this is cool.
Is this how you feel
all the time?
Because, you know...
Except for now, of course.
- Riley!
- All right.
What I know is that
daylight savings
wasn't established until
World War I.
If it's 3pm now, OK, that means
in 1776, it would be 2pm.
- Let's go.
- Riley, you're a genius.
Yeah.
Do you actually know
who the first person
to suggest daylight
savings was?
- Benjamin Franklin.
Is this real?
Just tell me what you
told my friend.
Just a bunch of letters.
I can't remember.
Can you remember which ones
you were gonna tell him next?
Yeah, here. S-T-O-W.
Top results: Liberty Bell
and Independence Hall.
Imagine its impact
back in the 18th century.
It could have been seen
for miles around,
which was exactly its purpose,
because it served as a beacon,
as it were,
for people to collect and hear...
Good stuff.
It was in 1846 on George
Washington's birthday
that the final expansion of
the crack occured,
retiring the Liberty Bell
permanently.
Eventually,
it was moved from its place
in Independence Hall steeple
and given its own...
- Idiot.
- Who?
- Me.
- What?
It's not here. It's there.
Come on.
- What bell is this?
- It's the Centennial Bell.
It replaced the Liberty Bell in 1876.
There it is.
All right. I'm gonna go
down there,
and you meet me
in the signing room.
- OK? All right.
- OK.
All right, let's go.
3:22. My idea.
Hey. What'd you score?
I found this.
Some kind of ocular device.
"The vision to see
the treasured past."
Let me take this.
Aw, they're like early
American X-ray specs.
Benjamin Franklin invented
something like these.
I think he invented these.
So, what do we do with them?
We look through it.
Here, help me.
- Careful.
- You think?
What?
It's just that the last time
this was here
it was being signed.
Ben, there's another
tour coming.
Turn it over.
- Careful.
- Spectacles.
What do you see?
What is it?
Is it a treasure map?
It says, "Heere at the wall",
spelled with two E's.
Take a look.
Wow.
Why can't they just say,
"Go to this place,
and here's the treasure,
spend it wisely"?
Oh, no.
- Oh, no.
How'd they find us?
Well, Ian has nearly
unlimited resources.
And he's smart.
I don't think we can get out of
here without being spotted.
Well, we don't want them
to have the Declaration,
or the glasses.
And we especially
don't want them
to have them both together.
So what do we do?
We separate the lock
from the key.
- We're splitting up.
- Good idea.
Really?
I'll take this.
And those.
You keep that.
Meet me at the car and call me
if you have any problems.
Like if we get caught
and killed?
Yeah. That would be
a big problem.
Take care of her.
- I will.
We're on him.
There he is.
- Let's walk this way.
- Wait up.
- Shaw, look. There's the others.
- I got it.
Viktor, meet me
at Fifth and Chestnut.
Fifth and Chestnut.
They're heading your way.
- Look out! Look out!
- Riley!
- There they are! Move!
- Move!
Time to run.
Keep up, Viktor!
Move. Come on.
In here.
- Come on.
- Follow me.
That way.
If you're not a steak,
you don't belong here.
I'm just trying to hide
from my ex-husband.
- Who, baldy?
- Yes.
Honey,
stay as long as you like.
Oh, thank you. Thank you.
You want something?
- Do you want something?
- Shut up.
I see why you left him.
Go around. Go around.
Gates!
Aw, come on!
- Where were you?
- Hiding.
Come on. Let's go, let's go.
Ian. Ian, I've got 'em.
They're heading toward
City Hall.
- OK, I'm on my way.
- Out of the way!
They're headed for the
breezeway on the north side.
I'll be right there.
Hey, Gates!
Enough, man!
Give me the document.
All right, Phil.
Watch out!
Get out of my way!
Watch it!
Leave them! Let 'em go.
We've got it.
FBI.
Have you seen this guy?
No.
Nope, I haven't seen him.
Ted. Philadelphia police
found Gates's car.
It's close.
We got surveillance there now.
Let's go. Tell the boss
we got the car.
- What?
- We lost it.
What?
We lost the Declaration.
Ian took it.
Yeah, OK. You all right?
You both all right?
Yeah, yeah, we're all right.
- Ben, I'm sorry.
- We'll be fine.
Meet me at the car.
Suspect has arrived.
Hello, Mr Gates.
Mr Gates,
face your father's car
and put your hands behind
your back, please.
We got one in custody.
Gates,
you're a hard man to find.
Could you please be careful?
Riley, do you know
how to get in touch with Ian?
Excuse me?
That's some story.
Well, it's the same story
I tried to tell you guys
before the Declaration
was stolen.
- By you.
- No, by Ian.
I stole it to stop him.
I did it alone.
Dr Chase was not involved.
And Ian still ended up with the
Declaration of Independence.
Because of you.
So here's your options.
Door number one,
you go to prison
for a very long time.
Door number two,
we are going to get back the
Declaration of Independence,
you help us find it,
and you still go to prison
for a very long time,
but you feel better inside.
Is there a door that
doesn't lead to prison?
Someone's got to
go to prison, Ben.
Yeah.
So what are these for?
It's a way to read the map.
Right.
Knights Templar.
Freemasons.
Invisible treasure map.
- So what'd it say?
- "Heere at the wall."
Nothing else.
It's just another clue.
It looks like Ian Howe
could be a false identity.
Follow up with ATF and INS.
There's more to it.
- Standard tap procedure.
- Let's check the signal, folks.
- Lock it in.
- Are we set?
- Checking source.
- Unknown number.
Yes.
Hello, Ben. How are you?
- Um, chained to a desk.
- Sorry to hear that.
I want you to meet me on the
flight deck of the USS Intrepid.
- You know where that is?
- New York.
Meet me there at ten o'clock
tomorrow morning.
And bring those glasses you
found at Independence Hall.
Yeah, I know about
the glasses.
We can take a look
at the Declaration,
and then you can
be on your way.
And I'm supposed to
believe that.
I told you from the start,
I only wanted to borrow it.
You can have it.
And the glasses.
I'll even throw in the pipe
from the Charlotte.
I'll be there.
And tell the FBI agents
listening in on this call
if they want
the Declaration back,
and not just
a box of confetti,
then you'll come alone.
- Take positions.
- Perimeter looks normal.
Can I get a status report?
Crow's nest in position.
Port side is quiet.
Copy that.
- Gates is on the flight deck.
- Eyes on Gates.
- Do not lose sight of primary mark.
- Brian, you're clear with NYPD.
- I have a visual.
- Gates.
Stay with the program.
I hope your agents are
all under four feet tall
and wearing little scarves.
Otherwise Ian's gonna
know they're here.
As soon as he shows
you the Declaration,
we'll move in.
Don't try anything.
Just let us handle it.
You know, Agent Sadusky,
something I've noticed
about fishing:
It never works out
so well for the bait.
Sir, we've got some
traffic incoming.
Looks like a sightseeing
helicopter.
Unit two, get an eyeball
on that chopper.
Agent Michaels,
get FAA flight plans
and authorization records
on that craft.
If that's not Mr Howe,
I want to know who it is.
I got him.
He's coming from the north.
Gates. Are you with me?
Well, I'm sure not against you,
if that's what you're asking.
We've got some interference
on Gates's mike, sir.
This I know.
Hello, Ben.
Thomas Edison needed only
one way to make a light bulb.
Sound familiar?
- Keep sightlines clear.
- What's the devil's going on here?
There's a lot of commotion.
We can't see Gates.
Go to the starboard observation
point behind the F-16
and here's what you do.
Gates? Gates?
Air Tour helicopter,
you are in controlled airspace.
Vacate immediately.
Who's got Gates?
- All agents, report in.
- I can't see anything.
- Did Gates speak to anybody?
- Target is moving.
He's heading towards
the stern.
I've got him.
He's coming this way.
Anyone got a view of
our friend Ian Howe?
Ian Howe is not
at the stern, sir.
Then why is he heading there?
He's at the observation deck.
Sadusky.
I'm still not against you.
But I found door
number three.
And I'm taking it.
- What's he talking about?
- Move in!
Move in!
Move in on Gates!
Divers are a go.
- Snipers, go to action zebra.
- All teams, move in.
Pursue at own risk.
- I repeat, pursue at own risk.
- You first.
Holy mackerel. He set us up.
Agent Dawes,
do you have a visual?
Can you see Gates
in the water?
Sir, it's the Hudson.
Nothing is visible.
Smart fish.
Hello, Ben.
Welcome to New Jersey.
What'd you do with
Abigail and Riley?
Hope these fit.
We had to guess your sizes.
I said, what'd you do
with Abigail and Riley?
He's the only one who could've
told you that line about Edison.
Did you bring the glasses?
I don't know. Tell me
what's happening here.
Ask your girlfriend.
She's the one calling
all the shots now.
She won't shut up.
Yeah, hello.
It's for you.
Hello.
Hi, sweetie.
How's your day going?
Uh, interesting, dear.
So, what,
you working with Ian now?
It turns out helping someone
escape from FBI custody
is a criminal act.
And he's the only
criminal we knew.
So we called him and
made a deal.
You're... you're...
you're all right, yeah?
I mean you're safe?
Yeah, we both are.
Riley's right here,
doing something clever
with a computer.
I'm tracking him through the...
Hey!
I'm tracking you through
the GPS in Shaw's phone.
They take a turn anywhere
we don't want,
we'll know it.
So don't worry.
If Ian tries to double-cross us,
we can call the FBI and tell
them right where you are.
- And where to find Ian.
- And where is that?
Right across the street
from where we're hiding,
at the intersection of
Wall Street and Broadway.
Well, you figured out the clue.
Simple. "Heere at the wall."
Wall Street and Broadway.
Ben, there is a catch.
We made Ian believe
he could have the treasure.
It was the only way
we could get this far.
He's here.
Here we go.
Ben.
You all right? No broken bones?
A jump like that could kill a man.
Naw, it was cool.
You should try it sometime.
The Declaration of Independence.
And the meerschaum pipe.
All yours.
- That's it?
- That's it.
I knew you'd keep
your promise.
Now, where is it?
Where's my treasure?
It's right here.
The map said
"Heere at the wall",
spelled with two E's.
Wall Street follows the path
of an actual wall
that the original Dutch settlers
built as a defence
to keep the British out.
The main gate was located
at a street called De Heere,
also two E's.
Later De Heere Street
was renamed Broadway
after the British got in.
So, "Heere at the wall."
Broadway, Wall Street.
Cheerio.
Just a moment, Ben.
Ian, if you break our deal,
the FBI will be only
a few minutes behind you.
You might get away,
you might not.
Is that all the map said?
Every word.
Oh, Ben.
You know the key to
running a convincing bluff?
Every once in a while you've
got to be holding all the cards.
Dad.
Is there anything else
you want to tell me?
Trinity Church.
We have to go
inside Trinity Church.
Good. Excellent.
Well, why don't you ask
Dr Chase and Riley to join us?
I'm sure they're around
here somewhere.
Are you all right?
What do you think?
I'm a hostage.
Sit. Sit down.
- Let him go, Ian.
- When we find the treasure.
No, now.
Or you can figure out
the clues for yourself.
Good luck.
Ben.
I don't think
you fully appreciate
the gravity of the situation.
Let's have a look at that map.
It's...
It's... it's really quite something.
It really is remarkable.
Take a look.
- "Parkington Lane."
- "Beneath Parkington Lane."
But why would the map
lead us here,
then take us
somewhere else?
- What's the purpose?
- Just another clue.
Dad. No, you're right.
Parkington Lane
has to be here somewhere.
- A street inside the church?
- Not inside. Beneath.
Beneath the church.
- I'm so sorry, Ben.
- None of this is your fault.
- I co...
- Come on.
Look.
Cooperation only lasts as long
as the status quo is unchanged.
As soon as this guy gets to
wherever this thing ends,
he won't need you any more.
Or... or any of us.
So we find a way to
make sure
the status quo
changes in our favour.
- How?
- I'm still working on it.
Well, I guess I better
work on it too, then.
Hey! Par... Hey, I found it!
- Him!
- Ben!
It's a name.
Parkington Lane.
He was a third-degree master
mason of the Blue Lo...
Hey! Stop!
Easy.
Careful no one steps in him.
All right, put it down.
OK.
Who wants to go down the creepy
tunnel inside the tomb first?
Right. McGregor,
Viktor, you stay here.
And if anyone should
come out without me,
well... use your imagination.
Shall we?
You got a light?
Careful.
Watch your step.
Come here.
Why does that never
happen to me?
What's this?
It's a chandelier.
Here.
- Wow.
- Look at the elevators.
A dumbwaiter system.
How do a bunch of guys with
handtools build all this?
Same way they built the pyramids
and the Great Wall of China.
Yeah. The aliens helped them.
Right, let's go.
What are we waiting for?
I'm not going out
on that thing.
200 years of termite
damage and rot.
Dad, do what he says.
Watch your step.
We're right under
the Trinity graveyard.
That's probably why
no one ever found this.
What is that?
Subway.
Shaw! Oh, God, Shaw!
Oh, my God.
Hold on! Hold on!
OK, get on the elevator.
Jump!
Ben! Grab my hand.
- Come on.
- Ian!
Abigail! Get on!
Jump!
Here.
Ben! Ben!
Get down there.
Get down there!
The Declaration.
- Do you trust me?
- Yes.
Oh, no! Ben!
Hang on!
Son!
I'm sorry.
I'm sorry I dropped you.
I had to save the Declaration.
No, don't be.
I would have done exactly
the same thing to you.
Really?
I would have
dropped you both.
Freaks.
Get on.
Ian...
it's not worth it.
Do you imagine any one
of your lives
is more valuable to me
than Shaw's?
We go on.
The status quo.
Keep the status quo.
- Now what?
- This is...
This is where it all leads.
OK, let's go.
What is this?
So where's the treasure?
Well?
This is it?
We came all this way
for a dead end?
Yes.
There's gotta be
something more.
Riley, there's nothing more.
- Another clue, or...
- No, there are no more clues!
That's it, OK? It's over!
End of the road.
The treasure's gone.
Moved.
Taken somewhere else.
You're not playing
games with me,
are you, Ben?
You know where it is.
No.
OK, go.
Hey, wait a minute.
- Hey! Ian, wait!
- Wait, wait, wait!
- Ian...
- We'll be trapped.
- Don't do this.
- You can't just leave us here.
Yes, I can.
Unless Ben tells me
the next clue.
There isn't another clue.
Ian, listen.
Why don't you come
back down here
and we can talk through
this together?
- Don't speak again.
- OK.
The clue.
Where's the treasure?
Ben?
- The lantern.
- Dad...
The status quo
has changed, son.
Don't.
It's part of freemason teachings.
In King Solomon's temple
there was a winding staircase.
It signified the journey
that had to be made
to find the light of truth.
- The lantern is the clue.
- And what does it mean?
Boston. It's Boston.
The Old North Church
in Boston,
where Thomas Newton
hung a lantern in the steeple,
to signal Paul Revere that
the British were coming.
One if by land,
two if by sea.
One lantern.
Under the winding
staircase of the steeple,
- that's where we have to look.
-Go on.
Thank you.
Hey, you have to
take us with you.
Why?
So you can escape in Boston?
Besides, with you
out of the picture
there's less baggage to carry.
What if we lied?
Did you?
What if there's another clue?
Then I'll know right
where to find you.
See you, Ben.
- No!
- There's no other way out!
- Come back!
- You're gonna need us, Ian!
We're all gonna die.
It's gonna be OK, Riley.
I'm sorry I yelled at you.
It's OK, kiddo.
OK, boys, what's going on?
The British came by sea.
It was two lanterns, not one.
Ian needed another clue,
so we gave it to him.
It was a fake.
It was a fake clue.
The all-seeing eye.
"Through the all-seeing eye."
That means...
by the time Ian figures it out
and comes back here,
we'll still be trapped,
and he'll shoot us then.
Either way, we're gonna die.
Nobody's gonna die.
There's another way out.
Where?
Through the treasure room.
Here.
Riley.
Looks like someone
got here first.
I'm sorry, Ben.
It's gone.
Listen, Ben...
It may have even
been gone before
Charles Carroll told the story
to Thomas Gates.
It doesn't matter.
I know.
Cos you were right.
No, I wasn't right.
This room is real, Ben.
And that means
the treasure is real.
We're in the company of some of
the most brilliant minds in history,
because you found what
they left behind for us to find
and understood
the meaning of it.
You did it, Ben.
For all of us.
Your grandfather,
and all of us.
And I've never been
so happy to be proven wrong.
I just...
really thought
I was gonna find the treasure.
OK.
Then we just keep
looking for it.
I'm in.
OK.
Not to be Johnny Rain
Cloud here,
but that's not gonna happen.
Because as far as I can see,
we're still trapped down here.
Yeah.
Now, Ben, where is this
other way out?
Well, that's it.
It doesn't make any sense,
because the first thing the
builders would have done
after getting down here was
cut a secondary shaft
back out for air...
- Right.
- And in case of cave-ins.
Could it really be that simple?
"The secret lies with
Charlotte."
Scrolls from the library
at Alexandria.
Could this be possible?
It's a big...
bluish-green man,
with a strange-looking
goatee.
I'm guessing
that's significant.
Yes!
Riley, are you crying?
Look.
Stairs.
Hi.
Do you have a cell phone
I could borrow?
- Just like that?
- Just like that.
You do know
you just handed me
your biggest bargaining chip?
The Declaration of Independence
is not a bargaining chip.
Not to me.
Have a seat.
So what's your offer?
How about a bribe?
Say...
ten billion dollars?
I take it you found
the treasure?
It's about five stories
beneath your shoes.
You know, the Templars
and the Freemasons believed
that the treasure was too great
for any one man to have,
not even a king.
That's why they went to such
lengths to keep it hidden.
That's right.
The Founding Fathers believed
the same thing about government.
I figure their solution will
work for the treasure too.
Give it to the people.
Divide it amongst
the Smithsonian,
the Louvre,
the Cairo museum...
There's thousands of years
of world history down there.
And it belongs to the world,
and everybody in it.
You really don't understand
the concept of a bargaining chip.
OK, here's what I want.
Dr Chase gets off
completely clean,
not even a little post-it
on her service record.
OK.
I want the credit for the find
to go to the entire Gates family,
with the assistance of
Mr Riley Poole.
And what about you?
I'd really love not to
go to prison.
I can't even begin
to describe
how much I would love
not to go to prison.
Someone's got to
go to prison, Ben.
Well, if you've got
a helicopter,
I think I can help with that.
- Freeze! Don't move!
- Show me your hands!
- Put your hands up.
- Move, move, move.
You're under arrest,
Mr Howe.
We've got you on kidnapping,
attempted murder...
and trespassing on
government property.
Yeah. You got it, chief.
Thank you. Bye.
They want us in Cairo next week
for the opening of the exhibit.
They're sending a private jet.
That's fun.
Yeah, big whoop.
We could have had
a whole fleet of private jets.
Ten per cent, Ben.
They offered you ten per cent
and you turned it down.
Riley, we've been over this.
It was too much.
I couldn't accept it.
I still have this splinter
that's been festering
for three months from
an old piece of wood.
OK, I'll tell you what.
Next time we find a treasure
that redefines history
for all mankind,
you make the call
on the finder's fee.
That's not as funny.
What do you care?
You got the girl.
- It's true.
Rub it in.
Enjoy your spoils...
while I sit on one per cent.
One stinkin' per cent.
Half of one per cent, actually.
One per cent.
Unbelievable.
I'm sorry for your
suffering, Riley.
For the record, Ben,
I like the house.
You know, I chose this
estate because in 1812
Charles Carroll met...
Yeah, someone that did
something in history and had fun.
Great. Wonderful.
Could have had
a bigger house.
- I made something for you.
- You did? What?
- A map.
- A map?
Where does it lead to?
You'll figure it out.